A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Officers, RG 3 FA1797
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Correspondence and Subject Files, 1931-2017; 1; 12.65 Cubic Feet 35 containers
  - Crowe, Timothy, 1990-2003; 1.5; 0.57 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box and 1 half box
    - Correspondence re: Financial and Administrative Issues, 1994 April 13-1994 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Correspondence to and (mostly) from Tim Crowe including memos to the Finance Committee on the status of investments; monthly and quarterly financial reports; asset allocation comparisons; site visit reports; commentary on new laws and regulations and their impact on Knight Foundation.
    - Correspondence re: Financial and Administrative Issues, 1995 January 3-November 3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 3764
      Correspondence to and (mostly) from Tim Crowe including memos to the Finance Committee on the status of investments; monthly and quarterly financial reports; asset allocation comparisons; site visit reports; benchmarking analyses; a pension plan report; several KRI Research reports; and a memo on spending policies and investment planning.
    - Correspondence re: Financial and Administrative Issues, 1996 December 2-18 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 3765
      Correspondence to and (mostly) from Tim Crowe including memos re: timetable for technology projects; private equity investing; advice to new finance committee members; matching gifts program and KF contributions to employee retirement accounts.
    - Correspondence re: Financial and Administrative Issues, 1997 January 7-December 15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 3766
      Correspondence to and (mostly) from Tim Crowe including memos to the Finance Committee on the status of investments; monthly and quarterly financial reports; asset allocation comparisons; site visit reports; benchmarking analyses; the expansion and renovation of KF offices; technology projects; matching gifts program; and IRS audit results.
    - Correspondence re: Financial and Administrative Issues, 1998 January 14-December 30 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 3767
      Correspondence to and (mostly) from Tim Crowe including memos to the Finance Committee on the status of investments; monthly and quarterly financial reports; asset allocation comparisons; foundation asset rankings; an analysis of grant spending targets; a memo from Robb Kevers re: treatment of Program Initiative Expenses as adressed in John Edie's January 21, 1998 memo entitled, "Making a Grant to Yourself"; KRI analyses; benchmarking analyses; and a request for a proposal from Cambridge Associates for possible of outsourcing some of KF's investment work.
    - Correspondence re: Financial and Administrative Issues, 1999 February 2-December 9 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 3768
      Correspondence to and (mostly) from Tim Crowe including memos to the Finance Committee on the status of investments; monthly and quarterly financial reports; asset allocation comparisons; eBay stock; risk management program; KF and the impact of UBIT; staff issues; benchmarking analyses; and a reply from Cambridge Associates for possibility of outsourcing some of KF's investment work
    - Correspondence re: Financial and Administrative Issues, 2000 January 20-December 19 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 3769
      Correspondence to and (mostly) from Tim Crowe including memos to the Finance Committee on the status of investments; monthly and quarterly financial reports; asset allocation comparisons; Knight Commission financial data; and strategic planning.
    - Correspondence re: Financial and Administrative Issues, 2003 April 16 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 3770
      Memo from Tim Crowe to the Board of Trustees re: Preliminary Investment Results for First Quarter 2003.
  - Gibson, C.C., 1980-1988; 1.6; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
    Charles Colmery Gibson, President, 1977-1988. Mr.Gibson's eight files contain a letter recalling a discussion he had with John S. Knight on a theory about history (1983), a letter announcing the establishment of a scholarship for the Chopin Foundation in the name of Clara I. Knight (1984), and a memo to Cambridge Associates regarding the background and practices of Knight Foundation, including its focus, purpose, and preferences (1985). The majority of Gibson's files can be found on microfiche, or in Board of Trustees files (SEE Record Group 1, Board of Trustees).
    - 1983 Correspondence, 1983 January 20-August 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 791
      Letter from C.C. Gibson to Dick Capen of the Miami Herald recalling a discussion he had with John S. Knight on a theory about history; letter from C.C. Gibson to Eddie Thomas re: Akron grants and the community of giving in the Akron area; letter from Landon Knight, son of John S. Knight, to Gibson re: reimbursement of value of horse which died shortly after the death of John. Landon inherited John's horses.
    - Clara I. Knight Scholarship at Chopin Foundation, 1984 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 792
      Letter from C.C. Gibson to the president of the Chopin Foundation announcing that KF would award a $10,000 grant for the purpose of establishing a scholarship in the name of Clara I. Knight, the mother of John and James Knight.
    - Letters re: proposals and giving, 1987 April 22-1988 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 2506
      Letters from C.C. Gibson rejecting solicitations for funding; explaining the wishes of the Distribution Committee in awarding a few grants; and changes to the policies of grant-making.
    - Advice to James L. Knight, 1981 July 1-1982 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 2665
      Letter from C.C. Gibson to James L. Knight re: advice to Knight on assuming the Chairmanship of Knight Foundation following the death of John S. Knight. In it Gibson observed that "Jack didn't seem to get a lot of pleasure out of the Foundation, but that is no reason why you should not, if you can." Also included are two letters to trustee, Eddie Thomas, re: Akron community business.
    - Memos re: Comments for Foundation Meetings and Gannett Foundation, 1980 January 24-October 28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 2697
      Memo from C.C. Gibson to James L. Knight, Alvah Chapman and Charles Clark requesting, at Jack Knight's suggestion, comments on agenda items prior to the next board meeting. One agenda item, used as an example, was that "All comments received were in agreement location of headquarters should remain in Akron." A letter from John S. Knight to C.C. Gibson (who forwarded it to Charles Clark) includes Knight's revisions to the minutes of a special trustee meeting on February 14, 1980. Also included are two memos prepared in response to questions of the differences between Gannett's foundation and KF.
    - Knight Ridder News, 1987 January 29-May 7 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Knight File Number - 3896
      Letters regarding a Knight Ridder News cover story on the Knight Foundation and the possibility of ordering reprints for distribution by KF.
    - Meyer, Philip, 1985 November 2-1986 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Knight File Number - 3897
      Letters regarding Professor Phillip Meyer, who did research for the Knight Foundation, includes one from James L. Knight.
    - Background, policies and practices of Knight Foundation, 1985 February 13-August 30 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Knight File Number - 793
      Memo from C.C. Gibson to Cambridge Associates regarding KF's background, policies and practices (including its purpose, focus, and preferences), as Cambridge assumed the role of financial consultants to KF;three letters to trustee, Eddie Thomas re: Akron and Miami grants.
    - Background information on Knight Foundation, 1986 August 20 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Knight File Number - 2633
      Memo from C.C. Gibson to Lee Hills regarding KF's background, policies and practices (including its purpose, focus, and preferences).
  - Hills, Lee, 1970-1997; 1.7; 5.51 Cubic Feet 14 letter document boxes and 1 half-box
    Lee Hills, Trustee 1960-2000. His files are housed in fifteen letter size boxes and are arranged alphabetically by subject. The Knight Foundation Archives obtained copies of selected papers concerning the Foundation from Mr. Hills in 1996 when the Archives was created. After arranging and copying the papers, Mr. Hills's original papers were returned to him. These papers consist of Mr. Hill's notes, memos and correspondence created during his career as Knight Foundation's Vice-Chairman from 1960-1990, and Chairman from 1991 to 1995. The materials contained in the files document the creation and evolution of several key areas of the Foundation's operations, including Strategic Planning, the Cities Program (later called Community Initiatives) and its Advisors, the Journalism Program, as well as various advisory committees, policies, and grant making decisions.
    Three boxes contain grant write-ups for trustees meetings held between 1971 and 1986, a period for which there are no Board Books (where the write-ups are usually found).
    Lee Hills' notes taken at trustees meetings (filed under "TrusteesMeetings") contain information about planning for the future of the Foundation after John S. Knight's death in 1981. There are files on comparison visits to other foundations between 1981 and 1983 (filed under "Foundation Visits," and "Gannett Foundation"). Background information on the re-incorporation of Knight Foundation in Florida in 1993, the selection of future board members, and the deliberations over grant decisions are also included in the files.
    There are abundant materials regarding planning for the Foundation, particularly after the death of James L. Knight in 1991. Documents pertaining to planning can be found under "Consultants - Arthur Raybin Associates," "Committees - Planning and Program," and "Committees - Planning." These papers date between 1991 and 1992, when Nancy Raybin was hired as a consultant to plan for Knight Foundation's financial growth upon receiving the bulk of James Knight's estate in 1991.
    The infancy of the Community Initiatives Program is visible in documents dating back to 1974, under "Community Advisors," where correspondence concerns the issue of having local Knight-Ridder editors advise the Foundation regarding grant requests in their area. Later correspondence documents the expansion of communities served by the Cities Program, guidelines for the Program in 1988, and the evolution into the Community Initiatives Program in 1991. Also SEE Mr. Hills's Speeches in this Record Group for talks he gave concerning the Cities Program.
    Extensive documentation of the Journalism Program can be found in Mr. Hills' files, particularly related to the development of Knight Chairs in Journalism and mid-career journalism fellowships at several prominent universities, including Stanford, the University of Michigan, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and Northwestern University. The John S. Knight Fellowship Program at Stanford is particularly well documented. The files, dating 1971-1989, chronicle the formation, growth and success of the program.
    Finance materials in Mr. Hills' papers give insight into the management of Foundation funds and the legal responsibility of the trustees had in dealing with excess business holdings, and the 1989 bequest from the Dorothy Knight Trust.
    - Annual Reports - Correspondence, 1975-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Archives Project, 1987 December 1-1993 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 481
      Reports and memos re: creating an archives for Knight Foundation. Sarah Wright's report is based on a visit to a Foundation Archives conference. Also included are: survey and results of a Rockefeller Archives Center survey on Foundation archives; a memo from Sarah Wright to Creed Black, June 29, 1989, re: content of the permanent files; and a report by Ernst & Young on their assessment of Knight Foundation's records management program.
    - Center for the Fine Arts, 1984 June 14-15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 490
      Notes and memos documenting Lee Hills' trusteeship of the Center for the Fine Arts, directly relating to Knight Foundation grants.
    - Cities Program, 1985 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 491
      Draft of letter written by C.C. Gibson to Knight-Ridder Newspaper publishers re: the expansion of the number of cities preferred for grant distribution.
    - Cities Program, 1984 February 23-1987 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 492
      Correspondence re: Knight Foundation Literacy projects (background on issues, KF's interest in).
    - Cities Program, 1987 March 1-December 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 493
      Lee Hills' presentation notes, memos and letters re: planning goals for the Cities Program.
    - Cities Program, 1988 January 6-December 21 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 494
      Guidelines, report on grants to cities, memos on planning and goals for Cities Program.
    - Cities Program, 1989 March 29-November 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 495
      Creed Black's memo to editors in cities no longer supported by Knight Foundation; grids of grant obligations by city, 1989-1990.
    - Cities Program Advisory Committee, 1986 March 11-November 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 497
      Correspondence re: planning and guidance of the Cities Program.
    - Committees-all, 1981 October 5-1992 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 498
      Correspondence re: suggestions, guidelines, structure of Planning Committee, Advisory Committees for Journalism, Education, and Community Initiatives.
    - Committees, 1986 September 8-December 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 499
      Notes and memos re: committee to study reorganization of board and staff.
    - Committees-Education, 1988 July 11-1992 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 500
      Memos and list of advisors for Education Advisory Committee.
    - Committees-Distribution, 1988 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 501
      Memo to Distribution Committee re: ongoing grants for operating support.
    - Committees-Finance and Investment, 1981 August 14-December 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 502
      Memos re: IRS requirement of 5 percent payout annually of Foundation's assets, and items to discuss at meeting re: receiving Knight-Ridder stock from John S. Knight Estate.
    - Committees-Finance and Investment, 1982 March 4-18 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 503
      Lee Hills' notes on meetings; memos and suggested job description for chief financial officer. John S. Knight estate discussed.
    - Committees-Finance and Investment, 1987 February 10-August 19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 504
      Memos and meeting materials re: investments and spending. Comments from James L. Knight on items before Distribution Committee, and on Cities Program.
    - Committees-Planning, 1971 May 25-1982 June 28 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 515
      Correspondence on the creation of the Planning Committee, and its membership. Issues discussed include planning for the future of the Foundation in regard to Jack Knight's wishes that its headquarters remain in Akron, and that Knight Newspapers interests remain separate from those of Ridder Newspapers after the merger.
    - Committees-Planning, 1981 December 18 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 516
      Lee Hills' notes on Strategic Planning from 12/18/81 meeting. Issues include diversification of investments, payout policies and strategies, staffing, ideas for John S. Knight memorial, Journalism Fellowships (Stanford University).
    - Committees-Planning, 1981 December 1-1988 September 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 529
      Planning & Program related materials taken from board meeting minutes, 1981-1988.
    - Committees-Planning, 1985 January 14-15 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 537
      Meeting minutes and notes from Planning Committee (Program Review). Issues include decisions about Cities Program.
    - Committees-Planning, 1986 January 20-June 23 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 536
      Meeting minutes and notes from Planning Committee, including report on Gerontology by Barbara Knight Toomey, Education report, Statement of Purpose.
    - Committees-Planning, 1986 March 10 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 535
      Report to Knight Foundation Board of Trustees by Dr. Elizabeth Boris, entitled "Current Trends in Philanthopy."
    - Committees-Planning, 1987 November (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 517
      Memos discussing educational grants.
    - Committees-Planning, 1988 January 6-May 10 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 518
      Memos discussing planning of Education Program and grants.
    - Committees-Planning, 1988 January 15-December 14 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 530
      Memos, agendas and notes from Planning Committee meetings. Issues include Cities Program, health care related grants, Arts & Culture.
    - Committees-Planning, 1989 January 22-December 11 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 519
      Lee Hills' notes for discussion at Planning Committee meetings in 1989.
    - Committees-Planning, 1989 February 2-December 12 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 531
      Memos, minutes and notes from Planning Committee meetings. Issues include Arts & Culture program, Education program.
    - Committees-Planning, 1990 March 19-December 17 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 520
      Lee Hills' notes for discussion at Planning Committee meetings, meeting agendas and minutes. Issues include relocation of Foundation, literacy projects, policy on committees, Professional Journalism Fellowships at Stanford University.
    - Committees-Planning, 1990 June 7-October 22 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 532
      Memos re: Planning Committee and donor-advised funds.
    - Committees-Planning, c. 1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 522
      Lee Hills' material for writing "Knight Foundation Planning Activities and Background, 1950-1990". Includes KF history and background on its Strategic Planning activities. NOTE; DISCOVERED TO BE MISSING BY LCP 7/11/07. NOTE: Discovered by AB in previous box, returned to original location 2022.
    - Committees-Planning, 1991 February 11-July 8 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 521
      Materials related to Strategic Planning meetings with consultants from Arthur Raybin Associates. Issues include planning for the future of Foundation programs.
    - Committees-Planning, 1992 February 21-December 11 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 525
      Meeting notes and memos re: planning committee. Issues include James L. Knight Estate, Community Initiatives.
    - Committees-Planning, 1992 June 22 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Knight File Number - 526
      Lee Hills' notes for Planning Committee meeting of 6/22/92. Issues include free press, Latin America, Community Initiatives.
    - Committees-Planning, 1992 August 20-November 10 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Knight File Number - 533
      Memos re: Planning Committee meeting items.
    - Committees-Planning, 1993 March 17-December 14 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Knight File Number - 527
      Notes, agenda and minutes on Planning Committee meetings for 1993. Issues include Community Initiatives, literacy.
    - Committees-Planning, 1993 February 17-December 13 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Knight File Number - 534
      Memos re: Planning Committee meeting items, including National Community Development Initiative II, Knight Commission on Intercollegiate Athletics, Community Initiatives Advisory Committee, Newspaper-Related Foundations, Community Foundations Initiative.
    - Committees-Planning, 1994 March 3-November 21 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Knight File Number - 528
      Notes, agenda and meeting materials on Planning Committee meetings for 1993. Issues include Youth Violence.
    - Committees-Program Review, 1986 January 22-December 15 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 538
      Correspondence re: participation in Bicentennial of the Constitution and Bill of Rights project.
    - Committees-Program Review, 1986 February 25-August 20 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 539
      Memos, reports, discussions re: Gerontology issue.
    - Committees-Program Review, 1986 January 14-June 23 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 540
      Memos and notes from Lee Hills on Program Review Committee decisions, Gerontology issue, meeting minutes.
    - Committees-Program Review, 1987 December 21-1988 January 13 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 541
      Memos between Lee Hills and C.C. Gibson re: arts & culture and health care issues.
    - Community Advisors, 1974 October 23-November 11 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 542
      Memos and letter re: participation of local Knight newspaper editors handling requests and grants in their cities.
    - Community Foundations (Donor Advised Funds), 1985 June 10-1991 September 4 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 543
      Memos and correspondence re: Knight Foundation's involvement with Community Foundations in Knight newspaper cities. (Also called Donor Advised funds)
    - Community Initiatives Advisory Committee, 1992 January 1-1996 December 31 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 544
      List of members of Community Initiatives Advisory Committee in 1992, grant payout guidelines in 1994, summary of request for proposals for Immunization Initiative, memo on youth violence issue.
    - Consultants-Cambridge Associates, 1984 September 6-1985 April 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 545
      Correspondence with Cambridge Associates for financial consulting with the Finance Committee, including agreement on services to be rendered (reports on endowment management, collection of financial and investment information, investment planning), proposal.
    - Consultants-Arthur D. Raybin Associates, 1991 January 22-July 9 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 546
      Correspondence with Arthur D. Raybin Associates re: consulting for Strategic Planning, including outline of plan for work to be done by Nancy Raybin.
    - Consultants-Eugene Struckhoff, 1981 November 9-1982 October 11 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 548
      Correspondence with Eugene Struckhoff re: consulting for helping plan the foundation's future programs, especially in the cities where Knight-Ridder operates. Strategic Planning issues, including growth of the foundation's assets due to the bequest from the John S. Knight Estate.
    - Consultants-Rod Petrey, 1991 July 6-August 9 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 547
      Correspondence with Rod Petrey re: consulting as legal counsel.
    - Education, 1982 May 26-1988 November 21 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 549
      Notes, reports and discussions on the issue of funding for private colleges.
    - Education, 1983 July 25-1984 January 6 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 550
      Memos on revision of Knight Foundation policy on Education Program, including issue of higher education.
    - Finance, 1970 July 6-1982 April 14 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 551
      Letters re: Investment Management, stock and bond issues (purchase of Knight Ridder stock for the Foundation).
    - Finance, 1975 October 9-December 10 (Box 4, Folder 1)